Hello.
Hello,...my gosh.
This is my this is my back-to-back talk I just did the what's new...csharp
...vb talk so I'm still on the adrenaline rush from that talk because
...just it's exciting everybody's, you know,...excited to be there and I was excited be there so,
about fifteen till the end of this talk is going slowly crash that
...that I talk to anybody okay so you are all the ones we're going out whereas where
people asking questions okay you guys were all coming up here to make sure you got seats so,
in that talk we talked briefly very briefly about
...analyzers built on the...compiler platform
...is a piece of this giant thing called project
roslyn the thing I put...quotes because often we still think of roslyn and,
we people still talk about the thing called rather is much bigger than api said
involves the compilers of involves the id...scripting and
...much bigger thing is also the name of open-source project on get hub right so,
arousal is still alive and...we're talking about very specifically here is a single
...compiler platform which is the api set that we built on top the csharp in
visual basic compilers to allow you to
introspection source code transformation of source code really...so you
could write smart things that deal with source code with csharp code so my name is
justin...I've been on that project for.
Too long no, not really it's so much fun but, it's...it's been since we kind of
kick the thing off about six years ago we finished up visual studio twenty ten and,
I move very quickly over to start working on this re imagining and
then during that time we should visual studio a couple more times and we weren't in it but,
here with visual stooges twenty fifteen we are in it right is there is a real
saying is alive and,
the notion of analyzers encoder where libraries we're going to talk about today and,
I'm we're going to build today are
in the box so how many people here just let me get a show
...I want so temperature the room because I don't really have a planned?
And, I want...a sense of what people are interested in
...talk with some folks over here they had some ideas how many people have tried to build a dot analyzer?
Okay, so, like a small handful of your close yes I know you building analyzer.
So, but, how many people here are just interested in like I want to...to build these things I know what it is I want to
get involved...start working on that...okay,
so,...I want to try and present this as something for you guys okay so if you build
...analyzer will try...triangle really, really deep but what I want to be as I want to be at
the talk where we spend most of our time encode away from slides
...show you big syntax tree diagrams are all the other theory that
...going to sit down and write code ever going to build some
...so I...this last time in the last session they put these slides of the front
for evaluations if you're in a bad mood right now you can wait till the end
...fine with that you're feeling pretty good go ahead three of you could snippet right here but,
seriously don't give...better view right now...just...
So, what is a code where library this is a name that we are attaching
...very important feature
of it's notit's a it's a feature that gets exposed in visual studio twenty fifteen but,
we expect this to be something that we build upon for years to come the
...code where library is library the provides guidance on correct use
through imbedded tooling and operates in the users coding...
So, imagine take a library and
that comes along with all of the extra bits and pieces it needs to have
an editing experience that helps you use the library use the api is in this
iteration of that for twenty fifteen that means analyzers which
produce things like squiggles in the editor on the error list in...may break your
build that sort of thing on the build server fx cop just sort of thing includes fixes for those
...can create fixes that go along with them in the future this might
mean custom intelligence if you have a strongly typed api that take strings, for example,
or has some notion of,
you know, convention for type names...like in nbc where you have...and that sort of thing you want to
make a custom intelligence you can imagine all sorts of things here custom formatting rules for
how you format calls to my api is...that's not in the cards right now
but that's in thinking for later we want to take this idea of code where libraries that
...tooling in the library itself or in the in
...delivery mechanism is packaging and,
take that a lot further so that's kind of the vision?
So, let's talk specifically about done...again, they're...on a
...compiler platform api as we built this system we wanted to make sure that we could
do this also in an efficient way so,
the analyzer api eyes are design to run during compilation as
compilation happens whether that's a command line or to the id...compilation is happening all
the time incrementally essentially as you're typing the aidid to make sure you get
to intelligence after pressing a dot or squiggles show up in a timely fashion
so while that happens as the compiler does actual phases of
compilation and binds identifiers and does all of that work is calls out to
dot analyzers so that it does we aren't doing work twice right so you don't have to write
...and say okay tell me about this thing no instead the compiler comes and says
all right I've cooked all this up now what you want to know right so we can do it efficiently?
The today they can be distributed via new get or vsix...vsix visual studio
extension there is a project template that you can install with visual
studio that through the through the extension manager that allow you to create one of these create projects for doing these
easily but, when you write a new get analyzer the cool thing about that because
...the magic package restore it go it flows with
your code resource control into the build server wherever that needs to be so if you track if you
tracker dependencies if you express your dependencies in your project with new get with
...get packages you can get analyzers to just kind of flow through
the entire system that way so that's why it's very attractive vsix is kind of...things
that maybe you don't want to go through the whole system things like I've I wrote...
project called the csharp essentials which is just helping you guide
you to using csharp six features are not necessarily the sorts of things you'd want to error on the build server
rather things like aided you could use an expression bodied member here, you know, that sort of thing so,
that one works really particular
...of vsix also something you wouldn't want to add every project you don't have on all the time so,
there's a couple different...mechanisms and they have different reasons for using them now dot
analyzers are used enforce best practices so, a lot of ways you can think of it as kind of the
Spiritual successor to fx cop in fact the team
is responsible for this we built several of the kind of the highest valued went did a bunch of
...picked out...the highest value fx
...rules that really get used a lot and add the most value into the projects and
converted those dot net analyzers so those and those are up...get as well so you can grab those and use them today and,
as I said before dot enablers analyzers may include code fixes those
what happened on the build server but they are they happen in the id...show up in a little light bulbs
everyone grid experience around okay.
As I...forecast vision library plus analyzer and fix that is a code where library
ok.
And, that is all the slides I've got four you.
And, you guys are easy.
Ok, so, if you are the last session I apologize I'm going to show this again I
need...showed again just kind...this up for everybody who has been here because we have such a large room
I wasn't expecting to have such a large room I'm really,
really delighted that there's this much interest but,
that means that I wanted to be a little bit more interactive and talk about what we want to build...maybe build on-the-fly.
...have to pick something to build and we're going to build is a set
of guidance for immutable arrays now before we build that I want to show a
couple of things that I think are instructive let's dig into.
So, it's most...first so we're...we're
...build analyzer a little bit but I want to show you what it looks like when you got one of the product so, this is.
This is a fun project people see my talks before they know that I like to
...to show of z machines.
They may nobody's nobody knows
...talk about yes one person z machine wasin
...a virtual machine perhaps the first commercially available commercial machine back in the early eighties
for running text adventure games written by the company info
calm in order so that the when you want to produce a game a text...game
...talking about go north...south pick up the soared kill the troll that sort of thing so,
when you when they wanted to create a game they would create a game file that was the
snapshot of initial memory for the virtual machine and then they would just create a
vm a different vm for every machine they targeted because back then if you want to have, you know,
broad reach of the consumer base...you're writing for the apple to
...for the tandy or writing for everything right
...so you need to have a broad set
of machines available to this help them with development this is...machine well,
I've gotten several of these this one is it's pretty glorious I personally think because it's a full
...that I wrote for this I'm a little crazy so if I...and run into this...see
...right there's just the code base I'm totally this is self-serving right now but,
I can open the mailbox hit a
break point step around through the through the code all that kind-of thing but,
...works in a run the whole games all these games so this is just my code base
and I want to look at right now and look at some
...analysis now I've gotten here what's delete something
I've gotten here I have installed csharp essentials csharp essentials is an extension
...for little...twenty fifteen to give you a set of analyzers just
a very few like three analyzers
...refactoring to allow you to basically point out and,
transform code that could go to csharp six...six feature could be
used if you want to fight it you can go to the extensions and updates from the tools menu search
...essentials it's right here we're using the last session...using this in the
last session to convert features so, in my error list?
I actually should have tons of problems.
...problems this is guidance given to me through this vsix that's
...visual studio is not part of the compiler but there are
literally.
A hundred-and-some things that I could do in this project if I wanted to
you csharp six features right now this is this
error list is something we completely rebuilt for visuals two-twenty fifteen
to make it scale to the several thousand errors and
warnings cases to make it easier to work with when that happens so that the short-order makes sense you get
...hopefully you get the real error up on top is causing all the rest of the errors when it comes to cascading
situations done a lot of work here to make sure that it's very
efficient at loading lots and lots of...because in this release with the release of analyzers we
wanted to we're going to do a lot more of that now if I come down to the wireless thing I'm actually going to
see some of these show up in the editor you'll see that certain things are great out kind of
faded out because this is a case where...analyzer that's doing that the same fade this
outright here because.
This if I...says consider use an expression body member here
...use the new csharp six feature that allows me...use the double
...the pharaoh to produce...expression by member of
...fix for it so when I look at the fix you see it right here.
And, you see this kind of...you what's very cool about this in very subtle is if you notice in that
...view the red part those are great out there.
Is actually what this is a using the roslyn object model because
...snapshot way I
create a code fixes I create a new version of that in the future at some point
...future crease and speculative version...fork often do something else so,
the features though can run on those that entire object model even if it's in the future so what
you're seeing that graying out there that's actually the analyzer itself running in the preview window
it's not like we just took a bitmap it's actually the real thing that's
...editor hosted in there and it's running right there but,
you can see what's going to do you get all of this for free when you write
a code fix and apply it and it goes way down below I can also
...code fixes so that they can fix at various scopes so I could say well fix everything
...this document and look at a preview of that and?
Watch my line count drop by about forty lines of code so
that's the sort of thing that you can do with code fix this one is all again with vsix.
There are several
...well that's one way of distributing and packaging these but I
think the preferable way and the way that most people want to distribute them is through new get
...this is a great way of doing it because you can ensure that you can have your own
new get packages that are used...you know, at your companies on your build
servers to for your own guidance your own particular things that you want to make sure that
your developer teams are adhering to the best practices that your in team enforces and,
then also for things that are out there that are come common libraries that people
use when they go get those from new get I want their tooling...what the squiggles and analyst analysis
come down with so back to this...I don't I apologize again if you if you saw this
...last are the idea here this code?
It's pretty simple what it's doing most people can see what it's doing it's you know,
open empty array you open array with five elements and you print the length of each one
okay very simple and when we're...to csharp new dot net this is a
...of thingthat we...this becomes very common we this is how we
cr world right...nobody's very surprised about that?
Now then what happens though is we introduce a new
library and you got all these ideas your head about how things work right and,
we introduce something that's conceptually very similar to something that you've been working with for years like
arrays so the thing I'm going to refer to as
...system dot collections dot immutable a package that we released with a set of
immutable collections it's got, you know, dictionaries and, in lists and things are all done
in a very immutable style so that when you add to them you get a new one back right and
there's a lot of sharing of items between them because it's kind of snapshot in...very popular but,
when using array you would think?
That you write-in very much the same way so here's the code
so aone down here is very similar to a one up here right you just
...one up you assume it's going to be empty right.
Down here, you know,
one up and you put a collection analyzer looks very much like this you assume that's going
to work but in reality if I have five this it will do nothing because I didn't run that code?
Because load watch me fail
all right so in this case though explodes
like badly no reference exception and it's not at all-clear why in
fact is very subtle why this explodes the reason is because immutable
...itself the reason was it's purpose for living is that so that can wrap around
...existing array an offer you kind of
...interface into that array so read-only sort of way to talk to it...got
ad methods so that when you add element to it you get back a new immutable array now
...because we want to keep the overhead very low on this it's...so all
...have public parameter list constructors that basically create
destruct with everything old out right just as if you said default of that
struct value it's the same thing if you knew it up with the public parameter...just kind of one of the
...the cost...the design of using a struct so in this case there is no
rate in it right now so explodes if I look at.
...at this.
Aone actually says it's initialized and then trying to drill into
it explodes even in the debugged so this is something that.
...api that should tell you don't use me this way this is a bad idea
...is not what you want it's not what you're expecting it to do the sort of thing that we would normally
...the compiler input and error writers who don't do this is not the does not what you want
is never going to work right interestingly on the
next line so if I were to say...
...this out on...and carry-on...continue on the next line I will also get
a no...because in this case it again is going to call
...public...constructor but even if it didn't.
It would still do the wrong thing even if this work even the public
...constructor actually constructed from immutable...that was just a zero.
Element array would still fail because the collection initialize are in csharp all
...does is compile down to a sequence of ad
...kelso...ad method and the ad method on amenable rate doesn't affect that immutable
...it returns a new one so what you get the end of collection analyzer is still
and empty array right so this very much also does not do what you think it's going
Wouldn't it be great if this api came along with that guides
with those errors so just yesterday?
I through a new get package up here.
You look at my all list we'll say
well I couple keywords oops.
That's not going
...anything ago so I put a package called core effects analyzers cortex
analyzers has to analyzers in it to detect exactly the cases I just showed you
so,... things that cost you right because they happen at runtime
they don't happen at compile-time in the editor when you're typing so they cost you time and money and
their problems right and they cause you to go and debugging figure out go whoops,...
and, then you're mad at me because
...and tell you right so instead of getting mad at me.
...install this new get package.
And, immediately or...close to immediately after things kind of
Squiggles.
...they just start showing up here and the...list.
There are.
To squiggles they say.
Useful things.
Do not use amenable to...doesn't tell you why we can make it tell you why there's,
there's there are facilities in the new get in the analyzers
...let you add more descriptive texture but,
do not use these do not use a collection...with immutable...in fact?
Let's go ahead and...quick fixes to show you to...to the
api you should have used so instead of knowing up immutable array.
Instead go and use the dot empty property which gives you back
...instance of immutable...that has no elements right.
So, we can do that.
And, then...here this one's a little bit more complicated to...the code fix
for but instead of using collection analyzer instead called create
range passing a new array that will be used as the array inside.
We go and now if I run this.
Things were fine and wouldn't...been a lot easier than seeing it happen
at runtime and not hating me...a lot easier on me?
If you guys got this to see the so what I want to do now...so this kind of setting
up what the problem spaces and I want to show you guys how to build these.
You want...okay, so.
We're going-to we're going-to go and create a new project.
I have gone installed this actually only show you again it's in this extensions
...updates I've gone installed the dot net compiler
platform sdk templates I also want install the visual studio sdk
...twenty fifteen rc to go along with this at the moment the visual studio
sdk is being itself broken up into new get packages so this is going to
change this idea that you have to go and find by this emphasize for visual studio sdk install that is going
to change so that you don't have to install that you can just install this package will have dependencies on the
visual studio educate packages so I install this and that gives me because
...now before we begin to
...building it so let's take a look at these lines of code
and what they actually look like there's another tool there that was right under
...another tool that is essential for this
message dot net compiler platforms syntax visualize are which is a tool window to install
...studio that lets you actually see the syntax trees underneath and all of the guts of what
the roslyn object models underneath and that shows up under view?
Other windows...syntax...right here I've already got it up so
I'm over here and click.
This gives me a view of exactly what I'm saying so here's
the local declaration...dig into the nodes of this the one looking for
...variable...into the equals value clogs and that's what I'm looking for
the object creation expression these names of these types these are nodes
...in...abstract syntax tree and, that these are nodes that.
Are have names that match the names in the seizure grammar we designed it that way so if you have a grammer up if you
have the csharp language...look...go up yes I...object creation expression...go over here
...node object creation expression so they...that's exactly what you have to know that you just
need to look right in here in fact this...got some real goodies if you
write click approachable and stuff so I can say view directed syntax...
And, then...of bringing up a graph
digital showing me the subtree of this whole thing.
Right which is super cool.
I can also come down here to the other local declaration...side.
And, see the invocation expression let's see simple member
access down into the argument list known over here.
Where we right here?
That the collection
...right this is the other thing that we need to look for so what I'm what I'm doing
...I'm kind of getting a sense of what the syntax tree is underneath the code that I need to go
and start matching and looking for an analyzer to kind of reduce second so
...can find the pieces...define and analyze them second-order shorts
...index diagram for this and
...very complicated so this...but this is a super useful tool
...I can also go ahead and I could change the code back to the
whether fixed and look at that and see okay here's what I need to do to where you
transform it into ok so there's a couple tools...really helpful here.
Now let's ...that code right there let's go ahead and create analyzer.
Some...analyzer with the code fix this comes from again from the extension that I install.
We'll call this.
As grabbing new get projects...packages right now and coming
in it also creates a test project to go along with it.
Candidly this is recorded...not can at all.
I don't really like artist...so,
I threw up a roslyn and unit like package that I can that you can use for doing if you want to
any testing arduous...x unit one as well just.
This creates for us though rather boxy creates for us ...
analyzer diagnostic analyzer
...a...dissension diagnostic analyzer coming from the roslyn api.
also exposes with...attribute so it identifies itself that will get load by the compiler.
And, also creates a code fix now.
When you create an analyzer there are some decisions to be made
first of all it doesn't matter what language you want to build and if you're vb person and you want to
Code fixes and analyzers that work for csharp
and vb that's fine if you're csharp person that wants to do it for csharp maybe that's fine.
I haven't tried...you could project with escher that's probably fine it's all dot net
code right at the end so it doesn't matter what language
you use but determining your target language may have some
you some decisions you want to make and what you have to kind of think about your analyzer and what
it does to determine half how language neutral or language agnostic can
be there are facilities for looking at for analyzing things in a
way that you could be make it work on csharp and visual basic,
for example, but, it's if you're...very sophisticated instruction...look very at
a very high-fidelity representation of the csharp code with the visual basic code the
...api is that case you might have
...split apart share some code that sort of thing if you want if you want to do that
whether various options you have available to this one in particular kind of looking at
the anatomy of a diagnostic analyzer the most important method here is the
initialize method and that gets called with this
thing called we call context and basically what this is a way that you can
get at interesting information at this phase and the way that oral and the way
you can hook up other events to perform analysis so that you want to be called on so,
for example,
I can dot into this and I'll see a number of registration methods and these are...I can
...up and event or call back to be
call by the compiler when it's time to do one of these things so
there's various there's various concepts you this code block which is when the compilers going
to actually do something that we contain a piece of code so you think
...body curly braces right that sort of thing was actually block of code but also other things like
...of a field or the value given to
of to attributes for the value given to a name parameter, for example,...
optional parameter those sorts of things are where code
...happens there's also compilation and, that's where it's going to the entire
processes starting the entire compilation process and, what these are useful for sometimes you if you want it really
...the syntax but also it compilation you can write things if you want to collect some state
right say I want to go and find all of the unused fields?
Right...do that you want to do a fair amount of analysis right so you have to
at the start of compilation you...some sort of data structure to go in-store all the fields
and collectible at the start and then I was...to create the data structure the
start then you would register actions to go through...look for all the field usage is when you found them you put
...in that data structure and then you would register compilation and action and when that happens
would go and do the analysis compare the data structure and say okay here's,
here's all the report diagnostics for all these unused fields ok so depending on the scope in the breadth of what you're trying
to depends on what you want to do here?
You can get pretty far we found.
With symbol actions symbols their to representations in roslyn
kind of universe there's a syntax representation
which is really like the nodes in the tree really relates to a source file
right it's got all the whitespace it's got everything in it all the comments all the nodes all the code but,
there's also a symbol version of it like a simple table work the
declarations go the types their members that everything can always think of as a review that looks like if
you're looking at reflection you're looking at method foes and types that
sort of thing that's what symbols look like cymbals tend to be very language agnostic and you can do a
lot you can get all you can get pretty far with symbols on fact a lot of the fx
...analyzers which do things like verify that if I've got
...reliable and interface and implementing and I
...added the serialized able attribute...a warning...code fixed
...your legible attribute that's something that and that analysis bring that squiggles something
you'd be done in a language agnostic way on symbols and work for both...visual basic the
code fix itself however because now you're getting into source code and the shape of how people actually
...code actually looks and it's very different that might have to be written separately.
So, what we're going to do this is a this is kind of a silly example I'm going to lead a bunch of bull
replete I don't want to any of this?
What this where does it gives you some...plate right up-front so that?
When you?
Basically what does it says you have types that don't have upper case
names or upper case letters or have lower-case letters in them and flags them with warnings that's the board-like code and
...to rename we don't need to run that we want to something more interesting so we're going
to do is we're going to register a syntax node action now the syntax
node action we're going to register because I want to do this analyzer to say if I'm
doing up and immutable array of t?
...using to them using the default constructor give-me as...that's what I want to.
I'm going to look for the arbitrary expression so all we're going to is coming here and say I use the syntax visual
either I saw what looked like outputs.
So, I'm going to register.
Syntax...action and,
that gives me an opportunity to add a delegating here or a lambda expression to say here's what I want
to do with this here's what I want to be called and usually what I
do here is I will actually often add a lambda and then.
I'll have I'll put some method name and here to be called afterwardsso,
analyze sorry object creation.
Actually this is not gobi called like...these get these are
...called with another context so I'll pass that in
And, then...very last argument
we create a list of the syntax...that we...look for so there's a new genome
in roslyn on both csharp in visual basic called syntax kind
it's very important one because it's crazy huge it has everything.
Ok, so, this is where I'd say yeah,
if you run into...object creation expression call my guy here
ok so I'll use a...from usage is...that for me
call this context over here and this one gets a different type of context.
The one above got this analysis context is kind of the place where everything starts
were initialize ing here's where you can register all the actions to kinda get started.
Now that I'm in here and I'm doing some actual work the context is a syntax
node analysis context and it's got different things on it has a cancellation token because my
...analyzer may or may not be run single threaded it may or may not it
may be running parallel somewhere else these are things you need to be considering,
you know, ...you know, careful track of state one of the reasons we do this action based approach was so that
you can nest actions and you can maintain state within those actions and keep it
safe right if we so that you don't have
to continually take locks but it's something to be considered because if you're in the id...chances are we're running
it asynchronous...so we're not blocking typing right so it's something to be careful so
passing cancellation tokens around is a good idea because somebody might type another character and your analysis
might now not be interesting anymore but.
The notice here the actual node the get return because we said we
wanted syntax kind dot object creation expression we know that's what it's going to be so we're
...we're going to assume that we get a set of options which are some sometimes can be passed
...now for analysis they're used for different differentsorts of.
Of scenarios...semantic model which allows us to
ask semantic questions at this point about nodes in the node or in the surrounding
...around so...when I systematic questions main like okay...take...object creation
expression that new of immutable array the first thing I need to do is look at the type of
it and verify that it's actually immutable array that would be the sort of question semantic question algorithmic
...is this actually will...seems pretty simple, you know,
about so I'm going to assume this
...object creation expressions syntax.
All right now what I'm going to do is I'm going to.
I'm going-to try and this is starting to get a little bit well, first we're going to organize the...
a little less productive and I'd like to because we're being able speculative about it I'm going to try and
write this analyzer at debug time with...continue because I find that is
...more efficient but first...plus...some better names up here before
you before dive into that let's give it a better category it's not naming
we're calling this like api guidance and then let's make sure that are resources makes sense I don't want to
be type names should be all upper case...to be use
...or don't use amenable rarity right ...
Instructor and will?
We'll just make sure that everybody realizes real saying I'm not just running the one that I had a new get
...slight-of-hand who write the real thing.
Now copy all...down here oops.
I see what did I was in here okay sorry about that.
All right there we go so now I'm just going-to go ahead and run
now if you notice down there the startup project is a vsix.
This is really great for debugging because I'm going to debug this against another instance of visual studio
just going to have it running so that I can go and loads
...replying around and hit my break point...so five.
Hopefully everything builds.
We...visual studio mind-blowing visual...debugging visual studio.
And, this actually runs visual studio in another we call experimental
high ifvisual studio has a way of kind of loading itself another
...has a different set of extensions so this doesn't installed my primary visual studio gets install
...studio with...other...of extensions that includes the one I'm working on.
If you're interested in error things ever get one key the best thing to do...air brake
...on the best thing you...everything's ever get walking with your highs.
Local app data prototype local...data.
Microsoft visual studio.
And, in here there's fourteen data that is twenty fifteen that's the version number visual
...doesn't fifteen that's my main...that's the one that runs when I click on the icon
in the start menu these are experimental once this is the one we're actually working in you can actually you can see the date
modified is today eleven six am it was one-minute ago when we compiler extension and, deployed
...so it's things ever get...you can come in here and do things like?
Delete extension delete the component model cash which does the math cash visual studio things aren't loading
right so there's there are things you can do here to kind of fix-up your world of things get out of...
whacked so prototype local at data microsoft visual studio so if...break point and,
the reason...break point was because...creation expression was found.
Right here's our demo fodder it looks like.
Looks like this.
It's not really much to it.
It was actually found if you notice this analyzer is running before
really even before the semantic polarization in the ide...
trying to find out is this is a scott is this thing bad so if I go ahead and step through.
Yeah, I see that in fact this is the object creation syntax.
I can look at it.
Here we can see what it is...strengthen see that yeah, that's exactly
...I'm looking for that's the node reagan always to string on a node and...give you exactly the source
code that was part from...even if it had errors will always go back and show you the same source code.
All right so next up we need to verify that is in fact
immutable array of t so I need to somehow figure out what type how to use
the semantic model to ask the question what type is this and I have to go out and find the
actual mutable retyping compare them are the same so let's get the
...retype first.
...mule retype because I'm not creative today and,
we're going to get to this by going back to
an api this is a very useful api for just trying to find.
Types in the universe...loaded go-to semantic model.
...compilation and...the type.
By its metadata name all right and the metadata name
of this type is system.
Collections...mutable.
Dot immutable array.
Who and what do I put here?
...it's not this...
it's not as meta name so in metadata if you don't know the way to generics are
encoded their names are...metadata was a backtrack and then with the array
...right so the number of type...will be back
...one and that should be the immutable array now because I'm doing this
...continue time just go back.
And, step over...make sure that worked hey look it came back with a symbol and name
types symbol system collections immutable...you
can start drilling into that and looking at the object model inside of it all right cool
that's cool so let's go to the arbitration expression all the bedtime all in continue
...so, let's ask that semantic model
hey the type of this object creation expression what is that.
So, I'm going to put that in a variable called symbol info and, I'm going to go to the context
...semantic model.
And, say all right and this semantic model has all sorts of interesting things on it
things that we will not drill into hear things like analyze data flow and all sorts of nifty things on
your forgetting asking semantic questions of syntax nodes that's kinda how we built
roslyn instead of giving you what we would call abound tree where or...antidotes
...everything all the symbols and everything was already resolved in the tree instead we give you an
api that you can ask questions what does this node actually buying to
what's the csharp language rules of resolved over it so I'm going to them holtz get symbol info.
And, that is going to be past object creation...creation expression of
...are actually because that's going back not the type of
...back to constructor so I'm going to drill into the object creation number grab
it's actually actual type part of the node the thing that's the actual...immutable rate of t.
And, we'll step over this.
Hey, look.
It's enemy...of system dot in thirty-two we're getting we're actually looking at
the source code introspective analyzing using this the...our of a compiler
done a compiler to...has done it compiler platform so now I know
it's a name type what I'm going to do here is I know I wanted to be
...types so instead of putting this in a symbol info I'm going to say.
We're...call this...rate type.
I'm going to get the symbol...it's a name type symbol okay that's what I
want to be will protect against it...a second so there
is my system dot and thirty-two so just plotted out that symbol info.
Now remember this is a construct a generic it hasn't internet already but the type
is actually in the assembly is the one that's of t sony to compare I wanted-to get back
from the one that's constructed to the open generic type to the one...of...so I'll do that
by using a property off of the symbol here called constructed from.
...gives you the returns types...this was constructed from without,
without type arguments if that equals the immutable
...type then.
We're going to reporter diagnostic one thing here is that if this happens to not
be the...type symbol for some reason and that is...conceivable could be
it could be other types of things it doesn't have to be immutable array could be anything if it happens to
be will throw here so I'm going-to go ahead you csharp six the noble condition
no conditional operator to make sure that I can it's just a scape that null so if it
has to be null will move forward now that is interesting because that changes
...this expression return boolean that changes this now to
null mobile have to change expression slightly say if that equals true.
Then we're going to go ahead and reporter diagnostic.
So, I go...the context I call report diagnostic.
And, I create diagnostic.
...actually we're going to...rule that's the diagnostic descriptor is define
force already it's right here is defined as part of the actual the template is
...with those resources that we that we renamed a little bit ago so remember that here.
And, the location is the span I want to be squiggles and the span I want to be scribbled
is actually the type so we'll give it a object creation again getting back to
...expression the type of it and we'll call get location?
one more thing I need to pass and...I don't need to do anymore things.
That's it.
Okay, we have literally this much code if
it's on-screen fifteen-point with a bunch of other tool windows up.
All right so just...to you let's go back here
...step over.
Here we reporter diagnostic I'm going to rubric point
...get to come back here and I should.
...google.
As a bonus we did all...continue now this...squiggles warning because
...default right that's the default from the...I could say it says, you know,
create these...warnings by default this is
a particularly heinous one I'm going to stop this and go back ...heinous,
...transgressions of using the immutable api so we're going to say
here it's over in the rule itself the default the diagnostics...should be
an error right so the squiggles read...your build so if you put this in a new get package
reprint of...sick or you put this new package...your project
and gets restored on build...on your build server will break your bill...great.
So, let's write a fix we've got a little bit time.
Yes,...time rather than the speed
though all right so I'm going to create a new code fix provider.
And, the way you do it's very similar to writing analyzer analyzers you're given kind of this
...the differences that analyzers
you're given api as the compiler has bakes them for you it's already
cooked them up so it hands over ok of semantic model now it's all cooked up I've done all the although I need to do
to resolve all csharp language rules here you go here it is in a code fix
...different it happens it's user initiated right so you kinda get a different set
of api is to work with it so.
I'm going to call this actually is a terrible name because
...sent from is that we'll call it build.
Build code fix provider we're going to sent from the type called
code which provider go ahead and control dot
to add that and then I need to always remember to export.
Okay, and, I give it a language
that is targeting so that's going to be off of there's a there's a type...of kind of a bag
of language names and rousing called language names...to be csharp.
So, this should be loaded now or...it doesn't error we get to a certain point will be
loaded in the id and we're going-to go ahead and implement that interface
or abstract class like so go ahead and.
Now the first thing to do is tell it here are the diagnostic aidid's that
it actually fixes a diagnostic ideas that little number that appears in the left...the
airlift actually totally a string you could you could put a lot of things in there but,
in for this one the diagnostic id is whereas
...up here.
So, I'm actually just going to the make it const...public
...so I can actually call it right off of this.
And, we'll just return a new immutable array half.
Careful.
What is create one passing in the diagnostic id from their?
...now this...out because hey csharp and schedules...this can be
turn into an expression by member sony to have all...position separate line
sometimes of the long ok now down at our method this is where we're going to implement
actually register code fix that's going to do the actual transformation
now what we're given in our context here this is a get
...a different context the code fix context is very different we're going to consul
the cancellation token the diagnostics for which this is being triggered because...fix could fix
multiples diagnostic...to be multiple diagnostics on the same line that apply so
...kind of a bag here a document now document is analogous
kind of to visual studio document or it might not be visual studio if
...hosted somewhere else it's and say so,
you're on a sharpe...something like that might not be visual studio but
...the that notion of a file with the tree and semantic model and all of
that you can actually though the document is also part of an immutable model object
model that can go up to you can get to the project into the
solution so you can do a lot with a document the documents triggered in you also get a
...which is literally the tech span of the that is being triggered off of
...so that's that location that we gave in the analyzer where do I want
this google to appear that's going to be right here is a spanned in the editor a start in and.
...we go and do we know we need to get back to that object creation expression so,
the first thing I would do though because implement abstract class does not do this
...I'm sorry?
The...asic...is going to run potentially, you know,
in the background showing up the
light bulb in visual studio it could...could run and all sorts of different ways so we do this
and is asic manner in the document itself is also supports of several asic api
as the first...is I'm going to get the syntax route from the document the syntax
...is what's from context document syntax...is
a little the root node of the entire syntax tree and it's a
Because.
It might hit the disk it might be this document hasn't actually been read yet in my have to go to the
disk do a parsed to all sorts of things so we do this asynchronous...we
await that so that we're not blocking the why thread while things might be happening like that
so we just to be aware ...cancellation
token case while that happens somebody types another character something like that now that we've got the
root of the tree we can take the span were given
and find the node that we're interested in so I'm going to do that by stream together a couple api
is object creation...what I'm going to get going...roots I'm going to find a node.
I think of...tree not...didn't do root ago
...a...find node pass in my span here.
And, that span is going to find me a node it might not be the node I'm looking for might because remember...actually
...of the type not the whole object creation expression the arbitration expressions
...replace and replace the new keyword in the parens of the end so we're going to go
and...tuff to can navigate through a find
the first ancestor of this in the tree or itself of type
object creation expression syntax...find for me.
that should be there now if we found that we know that this is were being called here because the analysis
happen we know that it's correct right we know that we are in...condition whether using
...array of t so we can go ahead and perform the transformation I'm going-to go ahead and
register code fix right here and we do this is you
...code action the code actions kind of representation of
the change itself okay the thing that actually transforms
...thing to another so...create that.
Credit code action.
...we'll give it a title like.
Use immutable array.
Dot-tdot emptied.
I would love...all of my fixes at that.
And, then we have a very complicated looking delegate types...
...lambdas doughy it takes a cancellation...returns a task
of document again because this is going to be a synchronous the transformation from the
old document into the new document needs to also be considered to be asynchronous as well so,
it's...return a task...document so I'm going to pass in here.
Name I cancellation token see and,
do fix we'll call it going to...in?
Let's see my object creation expression marcos over that I'm also going to close
over the document and my cancellation open.
That's all I need to do now I'm going to generate my method.
...have to make it a...
...do...have an extra.
So, yes.
Sorry...actually pass the diagnostic it likes to know which diagnostic
your providing a fix for there's only one and here's what provide that okay so,
now performing the fix I've got the...creation expression I'm going to construct.
The immutable array of t...of
...or whatever it's actually constructed from whatever...generic is I'm...to take that and
put dot empty on the end now I know that in the seizure grammer well,...just try it out I know the
seizure...that's actually a member access expression I can verify that bring up the syntax
visualize again.
And, looking just running some code and looking at it.
Right here...a simple member access expression
is whiny deconstruct and replace the object creation expression with that.
So, we'll go
in here...as you can see our bit more complex or.
Go to create remember access expression I'm going to use.
Actually I'm going to use a new api that we've just added called
the syntax generator which is a great way for generating syntax nodes in a language
kind of agnostic sort of way for various types of
...nodes and one of those that is easy to create from it is in fact the
member access expression so go ahead and add this guy.
Me some there we go to get generator for particular document so this gives me
a way this generator object to add all sorts of
things to make syntax changes to a tree to actually make transformation
super useful for a lot of different tasks the one I want this
one member access expression what does it takes a node.
And, a name the name is going to be the member that's going to be dotted into the node is going to be
the object creations type right so I can actually just passing here
object creation dot type...the name empty.
And, now I have the node I need.
So, this point it's there's a fairly mechanical process
...let's go back going to get the root of the tree again
...just copy and paste because we have...visual studio.
But, I need to changes on that because I
pasadena specifically and I gave it my own cancellation token called see all right so we get the
route.
And,...were going to create a new route from that...half by calling replace
node which can replace in the tree arbitration with
remember access and now we have a brian nutri back roslyn transformations
of syntax trees are done in a in of immutable fashion these are immutable
api so you think of it like string dot replace I make a change I get back in new
...the same thing with the trees.
And, then our last thing is we're going to go document returned from a document.
Document with that new syntax route.
And, now let's fingers cross.
Let's run.
May have done this in time.
Demo father here we are it's an error now like we said.
I'm not seeing the code fix.
And, but, I know why...open that folder earlier and I said sometimes you get a kick
things.
...component model cash.
So, that means now it's going to...to
...of cash I believe what happened was the binary didn't change enough that realized there was something new
...right so, visual studio didn't really refresh it so now there's a
...there and says hey use...immutable the of
...empty fool and sure enough it works you got the preview for free everything for free.
I want to thank you guys were actually at a time
...was a lot of fun rushing through and constructing something off the top
my head almost quite literally built yesterday so there's a few
relates ox obviously these are over but, these will all be online
...out dually even evaluation and...going to be
...to take questions we're kind of time if we want to use the microphones...please do so-if not
you can showed...try and repeat the question but I hope you guys enjoy it.